<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: School | Codemaster Extraordinaire]]></title>
  <link href="http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/categories/school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://vanessadean.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-20T22:30:17-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://vanessadean.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Vanessa Dean]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ajax and the Race Condition]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/08/20/ajax-and-the-race-condition/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T21:24:01-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/08/20/ajax-and-the-race-condition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week at the Flatiron School (our last week, aaaahhhhhh!) we&rsquo;ve been covering some standard computer science topics like big O notation, linked lists and race condition. So far I haven&rsquo;t used linked lists in any applications and I&rsquo;ve been spared worries about big O and time complexity, but the race condition is something that I&rsquo;ve contended with.</p>

<p>The race condition is a problem programmers face when the output of a program is dependent on a sequence of events, but those events are not completed in the order that the programmer intended. The specific problem that I encountered with my team centered on two events:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>A function that calculated a specific stopping point on a travel route provided via the Google Maps API</p></li>
<li><p>An ajax call to the Yelp API for restaurants near that stopping point</p></li>
</ol>


<p>The functions were being called in the appropriate order, but the second function kept firing off before the first function could finish its calculation of the requisite latitude and longitude coordinates for the Yelp search. Luckily our TA <a href="http://www.kthffmn.com/">Katie Hoffman</a> was on hand to provide some advice on addressing the issue. For details on how we managed the problem check out Catherine Meyers' spicy little blog post &ndash; <a href="http://anunexpectedcoder.com/blog/2014/08/10/premature-ajaxulation/">Premature Ajaxulation</a> &ndash; and see the results in action by checking out our app here: <a href="http://best-stop.herokuapp.com">Best Stop</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting Up Action Mailer With Mandrill]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/08/14/setting-up-action-mailer-with-mandrill/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-14T10:59:25-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/08/14/setting-up-action-mailer-with-mandrill</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Setting up action mailer with Mandrill, like so many other things in Rails, is incredibly easy if you know exactly what you are supposed to do. If you are doing it for the first time though it&rsquo;s hard to know where to go for instructions. So here they are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Follow the instructions in the rails guide to set up <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/action_mailer_basics.html">action mailer</a></li>
<li>Sign up with <a href="http://mandrill.com/">Mandrill</a></li>
<li>Create an API key (at the time of this was under settings > SMTP &amp; API Info)</li>
<li>Follow Mandrill&rsquo;s instructions on <a href="http://help.mandrill.com/entries/21738467-Using-Mandrill-s-SMTP-integration-with-Web-Frameworks">integrating with Ruby on Rails</a></li>
</ul>


<p>This mainly consists of adding this to your config files:</p>

<p>```ruby
  config.action_mailer.smtp_settings = {</p>

<pre><code>:address   =&gt; "smtp.mandrillapp.com",
:port      =&gt; 25, # ports 587 and 2525 are also supported with STARTTLS
:enable_starttls_auto =&gt; true, # detects and uses STARTTLS
:user_name =&gt; "MANDRILL_USERNAME",
:password  =&gt; "MANDRILL_PASSWORD", # SMTP password is any valid API key
:authentication =&gt; 'login', # Mandrill supports 'plain' or 'login'
:domain =&gt; 'yourdomain.com', # your domain to identify your server when connecting
</code></pre>

<p>  }
```</p>

<p>Then mail away!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Made a Really Important App]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/07/24/i-made-a-really-important-app/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-24T21:34:55-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/07/24/i-made-a-really-important-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last couple of weeks studying Rails and JavaScript have been a little rough. I&rsquo;ve been feeling frustrated and having trouble staying motivated. So this week I decided to drop back into Sinatra to build a little app that would make me feel better.</p>

<div style="margin: 0, auto;"><a href="http://buck-up.herokuapp.com/">Here it is.</a></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Little Help From My (Flatiron) Friends]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/07/19/a-little-help-from-my-flatiron-friends/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-19T14:16:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/07/19/a-little-help-from-my-flatiron-friends</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our seventh week at Flatiron School just flew by and we&rsquo;ve started studying JavaScript (on top of Rails). So much information is getting crammed into my brain that I&rsquo;m a little worried about losing track of the basics. I know that there are a ton of helpful resources out there, but some of my favorites are the blog posts that my fellow students have written. We are all roughly in the same place as noobies so their perspectives and insights are especially helpful. I&rsquo;ve been keeping track of my favorite posts in my bookmarks folder but figured it would be a lot easier to keep a few compiled here. Without further ado&hellip;</p>

<p><a href="http://ccmeyers.github.io/blog/2014/06/25/iterators-schmiterators/">Iterators Schmiterators</a>
by Catherine Myers</p>

<p><a href="http://callahanchris.github.io/blog/2014/07/17/five-useful-ruby-array-methods/">Five Useful Ruby Array Methods</a>
by Chris Callahan</p>

<p><a href="http://pcrglennon.github.io/blog/2014/06/10/rubys-hash-dot-new-and-%7B%7D/">Ruby&rsquo;s Hash.new and {}</a>
by Peter Glennon</p>

<p><a href="http://kylefdoherty.github.io/blog/2014/02/17/ruby-notes-working-with-files/">Ruby Notes &ndash; Working With Files</a>
by Kyle Doherty</p>

<p><a href="http://jbarrieault.github.io/blog/2014/07/02/error-handling-in-ruby/">Error Handling in Ruby</a>
by Jacob Barrieault</p>

<p><a href="http://www.korenlc.com/sql-cheat-sheet/">SQL Cheat Sheet</a>
by Koren Leslie Cohen</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Doing Well and Doing Good]]></title>
    <link href="http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/07/10/doing-good/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-10T18:30:38-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://vanessadean.github.io/blog/2014/07/10/doing-good</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;re at the halfway point at the Flatiron School and it&rsquo;s time to start thinking about jobs. I was curious about non-profit and social enterprise companies in the tech industry and here is a roundup of a few that I found during my research:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.donorschoose.org/">Donor&rsquo;s Choose</a>
Online charity organization that helps public school teachers raise funds for class projects. Based in New York.</p>

<p><a href="http://benetech.org/">Benetech</a>
A non-profit dedicated to developing technology focused on social benefits. Based in San Francisco.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.idealist.org/">idealist</a>
Networking site for non-profits. Based in New York.</p>

<p><a href="http://www1.networkforgood.org/">Network for Good</a>
Provides online fundraising tools to help non-profits connect with donors. Based in DC.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.crowdrise.com">CrowdRise</a>
An online fundraising site for individuals who want to raise funds for the causes that they care about.</p>

<p><a href="www.catchafire.org">Catchafire</a>
Matches professionals who
want to volunteer their skills with
non-profits who need their help. Based in New York.</p>

<p>No matter where I end up working, I definitely plan to give back through volunteering. Here are a couple of organizations in New York that I&rsquo;d like to investigate a little further:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.tealsk12.org/">TEALS</a>
Connects technology professionals with high school teachers to provide computer science classes in public schools.</p>

<p><a href="http://nycgenerationtech.com/">NYC Generation Tech</a>
An NYC non-profit dedicated to teaching young people technology and entrepreneurship skills.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sure there are a ton of other organizations out there and I&rsquo;m going to keep doing research.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
